So, can we dare to be optimistic?
إذاً، هل يمكن أن نتجرأ ونصبح متفائلين؟
Well, the thesis of "The Bottom Billion"
حسناً، إن فرضية المليار السفلى
is that a billion people have been stuck living
هي أن مليار شخص عالقون
in economies that have been stagnant for 40 years,
في إقتصادات ظلت راكدة لمدة 40 عاماً،
and hence diverging from the rest of mankind.
وبالتالي متباينة عن بقية البشر.
And so, the real question to pose is not, "Can we be optimistic?"
ولذا، فالسؤال الحقيقي لنطرحه هو، " هل يمكن أن نكون متفائلين؟"
It's, "How can we give credible hope to that billion people?"
وهو، " كيف يمكن أن نقدم أملاً موثوقاً به لهؤلاء المليار شخص؟"
That, to my mind, is the fundamental challenge now of development.
وذلك، لتفكيري، هو التحدي الأساسي الآن للتنمية.
What I'm going to offer you is a recipe,
ما سأقدمه لكم هو فاتورة،
a combination of the two forces that changed the world for good,
مزيج من قوتين اللتين غيرتا العالم لأفضل،
which is the alliance of compassion and enlightened self-interest.
اللتين هما تحالف التراحم وإستنارة المصلحة الذاتية.
Compassion, because a billion people are living in societies
التراحم، لأن المليار شخص يعيشون في مجتمعات
that have not offered credible hope.
لم توفر لهم أملاً موثوق به.
That is a human tragedy.
هذه مأساة إنسانية.
Enlightened self-interest, because if that economic divergence
المصلحة الذاتية المستنيرة، لأن ذلك التقارب الإقتصادي
continues for another 40 years,
يستمر لأربعين سنة أخرى
combined with social integration globally,
إلى جانب الإندماج الإجتماعي عالمياً،
it will build a nightmare for our children.
وستنمي كابوساً لأطفالنا.
We need compassion to get ourselves started,
نحن نحتاج للتراحم لنبدأ بأنفسنا،
and enlightened self-interest to get ourselves serious.
ومصلحتنا الذاتية المستنيرة لجعل أنفسنا جادون.
That's the alliance that changes the world.
ذلك هو التحالف الذي يغيّر العالم.
So, what does it mean to get serious about providing hope for the bottom billion?
إذاً، ماذا نعني بأن نكون جادون حول توفير الأمل للمليار شخص السفلى؟
What can we actually do?
ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل حقاً؟
Well, a good guide is to think,
حسناً، دليل جيد للتفكير به،
"What did we do last time the rich world got serious
" ماذا فعلنا آخر مرة كان العالم الغني جاداً
about developing another region of the world?"
حول تطوير مناطق أخرى من العالم؟"
That gives us, it turns out, quite a good clue,
ذلك يعطينا، كما وضح، فكرة جيدة،
except you have to go back quite a long time.
إلا أنك تحتاج للرجوع إلى الوراء لوقت طويل نسبياً.
The last time the rich world got serious
آخر مرة كان العالم الغني جاداً
about developing another region was in the late 1940s.
حول تطوير منطقة أخرى كان في نهاية الأربعينات.
The rich world was you, America,
كان العالم الغني هو، أمريكا،
and the region that needed to be developed was my world, Europe.
والمنطقة الأخرى التي إحتاجت إلى تطوير كانت عالمي، أوروبا.
That was post-War Europe.
كان ذلك بعد الحرب الأوروبية.
Why did America get serious?
لماذا كانت أمريكا جادة؟
It wasn't just compassion for Europe, though there was that.
لم يكن فقط تعاطفاً مع أوروبا، رغماً عن أنه كان كذلك.
It was that you knew you had to,
لقد كان أنهم عرفوا أن عليهم فعل ذلك،
because, in the late 1940s, country after country in Central Europe
لأن في نهاية الأربعينات كان دولة تلو الأخرى في وسط أوروبا
was falling into the Soviet bloc, and so you knew you'd no choice.
تسقط داخل منظومة الإتحاد السوفيتي، ولذا فقد عرفوا أنه لا خيار لديهم.
Europe had to be dragged into economic development.
ينبغي أن تُسحب أوروبا إلى التنمية الإقتصادية.
So, what did you do, last time you got serious?
إذاً ماذا فعلت، المرة الأخيرة التي كنت جاداً فيها؟
Well, yes, you had a big aid program. Thank you very much.
حسناً، نعم، كان لديك برنامج مساعدات ضخمة. شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
That was Marshall aid: we need to do it again. Aid is part of the solution.
كان تلك مساعدات مارشال. نحتاج لتطبيقها مجدداً. المساعدات هي جزء من الحل.
But what else did you do?
لكن ماذا فعلت أيضاً ؟
Well, you tore up your trade policy, and totally reversed it.
حسناً، لقد مزقتم سياساتكم التجارية، وقمتم بعكسها تماماً.
Before the war, America had been highly protectionist.
قبل الحرب، كانت أمريكا حمائية للغاية.
After the war, you opened your markets to Europe,
بعد الحرب، فتحتم اسواقكم إلى أوروبا،
you dragged Europe into the then-global economy, which was your economy,
قمتم بسحب أوروبا إلى الإقتصاد العالمي حينئذ، الذي كان إقتصادكم،
and you institutionalized that trade liberalization
وقمت بمأسسة ذلك التحرير التجاري
through founding the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade.
عبر تأسيس إتفاقية عامة حول التعريف الجمركية والتجارة.
So, total reversal of trade policy.
إذاً، إنقلاب كامل للسياسة التجارية.
Did you do anything else?
هل قمتم بأي شئ آخر؟
Yes, you totally reversed your security policy.
نعم: قمتم بقلب كامل لسياساتكم الأمنية.
Before the war, your security policy had been isolationist.
قبل الحرب، كانت سياساتكم الأمنية إنعزالية تماماً.
After the war, you tear that up, you put 100,000 troops in Europe
بعد الحرب، قمتم بقلب ذلك، وضعتم 100،000 من القوات في أوروبا
for over 40 years.
لطوال 40 عاماً.
So, total reversal of security policy. Anything else?
إذاً، قلب كلي للسياسة الأمنية. أي شئ آخر؟
Yes, you tear up the "Eleventh Commandment" --
نعم: قمتم بتمزيق الوصية الحادية عشر--
national sovereignty.
السيادة الوطنية.
Before the war, you treated national sovereignty as so sacrosanct
قبل الحرب، كنتم تتعاملون مع السيادة الوطنية كأمر مقدس
that you weren't even willing to join the League of Nations.
حتى أنكم لم تكونوا ترغبون بالانضمام إلى عصبة الأمم.
After the war, you found the United Nations,
بعد الحرب، قمتم بتأسيس الأمم المتحدة،
you found the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development,
قمتم بتأسيس منظمة التعاون الإقتصادي والتنمية،
you found the IMF, you encouraged Europe to create the European Community --
وأسستم صندوق النقد الدولي، وشجعتم أوروبا لإنشاء المجتمع الأوروبي.
all systems for mutual government support.
كل الأنظمة لدعم متبادل بين الحكومات.
That is still the waterfront of effective policies:
التي لا تزال القبلة البحرية لسياسات فعاّلة:
aid, trade, security, governments.
المساعدات، التجارة، الأمن، الحكومات.
Of course, the details of policy are going to be different,
بالطبع، تفاصيل السياسة ستكون مختلفة،
because the challenge is different.
لأن التحدي مختلف.
It's not rebuilding Europe, it's reversing the divergence
إنه ليس إعادة إعمار أوروبا، إنه قلب التقارب
for the bottom billion, so that they actually catch up.
للمليار شخص السفلى بحيث يمكنهم اللحاق بالركب.
Is that easier or harder?
هل ذلك أسهل أم أصعب؟
We need to be at least as serious as we were then.
نحتاج لأن نكون على الأقل جادون كما كنا عندئذ.
Now, today I'm going to take just one of those four.
الآن، اليوم سأخذكم لواحدة فقط من تلك الأربعة.
I'm going to take the one that sounds the weakest,
سأخذكم للخطوة التي تبدو الأضعف،
the one that's just motherhood and apple pie --
الخطوة التي هي مجرد أمومة فطيرة التفاح --
governments, mutual systems of support for governments --
الحكومات، أنظمة متبادلة لدعم الحكومات--
and I'm going to show you one idea
وسأعرض عليكم فكرة واحدة
in how we could do something to strengthen governance,
حول كيف يمكننا فعل شئ لتعزيز الحوكمة،
and I'm going to show you that that is enormously important now.
وسأبين لكم أن هذا مهم بشدة الآن.
The opportunity we're going to look to
الفرصة التي سننظر إليها
is a genuine basis for optimism about the bottom billion,
هي أساس أصيل للتفاؤل بشأن المليار شخص السفلى،
and that is the commodity booms.
وذلك هو إزدهار السلع الأساسية.
The commodity booms are pumping unprecedented amounts of money
إزدهار السلع يقوم بضخ كميات غير مسبوقة من الأموال
into many, though not all, of the countries of the bottom billion.
إلى الكثير من بلدان المليار السفلى، ليس كلها.
Partly, they're pumping money in because commodity prices are high,
جزئياً إنهم يضخون الأموال لأن أسعار السلع مرتفعة،
but it's not just that. There's also a range of new discoveries.
لكن ليس ذلك فقط. هناك أيضاً مجموعة من الإكتشافات الجديدة.
Uganda has just discovered oil, in about the most disastrous location on Earth;
يوغندا قد أكتشفت النفط للتو، تقريباً في الموقع الأكثر كارثيةً في العالم.
Ghana has discovered oil;
غانا أكتشفت النفط.
Guinea has got a huge new exploitation of iron ore coming out of the ground.
وقد حصلت غينيا على إستغلال ضخم جديد لخام الحديد المستخرج من الأرض.
So, a mass of new discoveries.
حتى تحولت الى كتلة من الاكتشافات الجديدة.
Between them, these new revenue flows dwarf aid.
فيما بينهم، هذه التدفقات الجديدة للإيرادات تقزم المساعدات.
Just to give you one example:
فقط لأعطيكم مثالاً واحداً:
Angola alone is getting 50 billion dollars a year in oil revenue.
أنغولا لوحدها تحصل على 50 مليار دولار سنوياً من عائدات النفط.
The entire aid flows to the 60 countries of the bottom billion last year were 34 billion.
إيرادات المساعدات الكلية للستين دولة في المليار السفلى في العام الماضي كانت 34 ملياراً.
So, the flow of resources from the commodity booms
إذاً فتدفق الموارد من إزدهار السلع
to the bottom billion are without precedent.
إلى المليار السفلى لم يسبق له مثيل.
So there's the optimism.
إذاً فهناك تفاؤل.
The question is, how is it going to help their development?
السؤال هو، كيف سيساعد هذا في تطورهم؟
It's a huge opportunity for transformational development.
إنها فرصة ضخمة للتنمية الإنتقالية.
Will it be taken?
هل سيتم إقتنائها؟
So, here comes a bit of science, and this is a bit of science I've done
إذاً هنا يأتي القليل من العلم، وهذه الجزئية من العلوم التي قمت بها
since "The Bottom Billion," so it's new.
منذ كتاب المليار الأسوأ، لذا فهي جديدة.
I've looked to see what is the relationship between
لقد نظرت لأعرف ما هي العلاقة بين
higher commodity prices of exports,
ارتفاع أسعار السلع الأساسية من الصادرات،
and the growth of commodity-exporting countries.
والنمو في البلدان المصدرة للسلع الأساسية.
And I've looked globally, I've taken all the countries in the world
وقد نظرت لكل العالم، وقد أخذت كل بلدان العالم
for the last 40 years,
خلال الأربعين سنة الماضية،
and looked to see what the relationship is.
ونظرت لمعرفة ماهي العلاقة.
And the short run -- say, the first five to seven years -- is just great.
وعلى المدى القريب -- لنقل، خمسة إلى سبع سنوات -- ذلك ممتاز.
In fact, it's hunky dory: everything goes up.
في الواقع، إنه شئ جيد: كل شئ يرتفع.
You get more money because your terms of trade have improved,
تحصل على أموال أكثر لأن شروطك التجارية قد تحسنت،
but also that drives up output across the board.
لكن ذلك أيضاً يقود إلى إرتفاع الإنتاج عبر كل المجالات.
So GDP goes up a lot -- fantastic! That's the short run.
إذاً فالناتج المحلي الإجمالي يرتفع بشدة -- رائع! ذلك في المدى القصير.
And how about the long run?
وماذا عن المدى البعيد؟
Come back 15 years later.
عد بعد 15 سنة لاحقاً.
Well, the short run, it's hunky dory,
حسناً، المدى القصير، كل شئ على ما يرام،
but the long run, it's humpty dumpty.
لكن في المدى البعيد، إنه سيئ.
You go up in the short run, but then most societies
تذهب لأعلى في المدى القريب، ثم بعد ذلك معظم المجتمعات
historically have ended up worse than if they'd had no booms at all.
تاريخياً قد توصلت إلى أسوأ من إن لم يكن لا إزدهار كلياً.
That is not a forecast about how commodity prices go;
هذا ليس تبنؤ حول كيف تتغير أسعار السلع.
it's a forecast of the consequences, the long-term consequences,
إنه تنبؤ للتبعات، التبعات بعيدة الأمد،
for growth of an increase in prices.
لتحقيق النمو عبر أسعار متزايدة.
So, what goes wrong? Why is there this "resource curse," as it's called?
إذاً ما الذي يحدث بصورة خاطئة؟ لماذا يوجد "لعنة موارد" كما تسمى؟
And again, I've looked at that, and it turns out
ومرة أخرى، لقد نظرت في ذلك، وقد تبيّن
that the critical issue is the level of governance,
أن القضية الملحة هي مستوى الحوكمة،
the initial level of economic governance,
المستوى المبدئي للحوكمة الإقتصادية
when the resource booms accrue.
عند تحقق طفرة الموارد.
In fact, if you've got good enough governance,
في الحقيقة، إذا كان لديك حكم جيد بما يكفي،
there is no resource boom.
ليس هناك طفرة في الموارد.
You go up in the short term, and then you go up even more in the long term.
أنت ترتفع في المدى القصير، ثم ترتفع أكثر على المدى البعيد.
That's Norway, the richest country in Europe. It's Australia. It's Canada.
ذلك مثل النرويج، أغنى دولة في أوروبا. إنها استراليا، إنها كندا.
The resource curse is entirely confined to countries
لعنة الموارد تقتصر تماماً على البلدان
below a threshold of governance.
تحت خط عتبة الحوكمة.
They still go up in the short run.
مايزالون عاليين على المدى القريب.
That's what we're seeing across the bottom billion at the moment.
ذلك ما نشهده عبر المليار السفلى في هذه اللحظة.
The best growth rates they've had -- ever.
أفضل معدلات النمو التي لديهم -- على الإطلاق.
And the question is whether the short run will persist.
والسؤال هو سواء كان المدى القصير سيستمر.
And with bad governance historically, over the last 40 years, it hasn't.
ومع حكم سيئ تاريخياً خلال الأربعين سنة الماضية، لم يستمر.
It's countries like Nigeria, which are worse off than if they'd never had oil.
بلدان مثل نيجيريا، التي هي أسوأ عن كون لديهم نفط.
So, there's a threshold level above which you go up in the long term,
إذاً فهناك مستوى عتبة الذي أعلاه تذهب إلى المدى البعيد،
and below which you go down.
وأدناه تذهب إلى الأسفل.
Just to benchmark that threshold,
فقط لتمثيل ذلك المعيار،
it's about the governance level of Portugal in the mid 1980s.
إنه تقريباً مستوى الحكم دولة البرتغال في منتصف الثمانينات.
So, the question is, are the bottom billion above or below that threshold?
إذاً فالسؤال هو، هل المليار السفلى أعلى أم أدنى خط العتبة ذلك؟
Now, there's one big change since the commodity booms of the 1970s,
الآن، هناك تغيير واحد كبير منذ طفرة السلع خلال السبعينات،
and that is the spread of democracy.
وذلك هو إنتشار الديموقراطية.
So I thought, well, maybe that is the thing
لذا فقد فكرت، حسناً، ربما ذلك هو الشئ
which has transformed governance in the bottom billion.
الذي قام بتغيير حكم المليار السفلى.
Maybe we can be more optimistic because of the spread of democracy.
ربما يمكن أن نكون أكثر تفاؤلاً بسبب إنتشار الديموقراطية.
So, I looked. Democracy does have significant effects --
لذا، فقد نظرت. للديموقراطية تأثيرات ملحوظة --
and unfortunately, they're adverse.
ولسوء الحظ إنها متعسرة.
Democracies make even more of a mess of these resource booms than autocracies.
الديموقراطيات قد تصنع فوضى أكثر لطفرة الموارد هذه عن الأنظمة الإستبدادية.
At that stage I just wanted to abandon the research, but --
عند تلك المرحلة أردت الإبتعاد عن البحث، لكن
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- it turns out that democracy is a little bit more complicated than that.
-- لقد تبيّن أن الديموقراطية هي أكثر تعقيداً عن ذلك.
Because there are two distinct aspects of democracy:
لأن هناك جانبان متميزان للديموقراطية.
there's electoral competition, which determines how you acquire power,
هناك المنافسة الإنتخابية، التي تحدد كيفية إكتساب السلطة،
and there are checks and balances, which determine how you use power.
وهناك ضوابط وتوازنات، التي تحدد كيفية إستخدام السلطة.
It turns out that electoral competition is the thing
وقد تبيّن أن المنافسة الإنتخابية هي الشئ
that's doing the damage with democracy,
الذي يحدث الضرر بالديموقراطية،
whereas strong checks and balances make resource booms good.
بينما الضوابط و التوازنات القوية تجعل طفرات الموارد جيدة.
And so, what the countries of the bottom billion need
ولذا، فالذي تحتاجه بلدان المليار السفلى
is very strong checks and balances.
هو ضوابط قوية وتوازنات.
They haven't got them.
لم يحصلوا عليها.
They got instant democracy in the 1990s:
لقد حصلوا على الديموقراطية الفورية في أعوام التسعينيات:
elections without checks and balances.
إنتخابات بدون ضوابط وتوازنات.
How can we help improve governance and introduce checks and balances?
كيف يمكننا مساعدتهم لتحسين نظام حكمهم وتقديم الضوابط والتوازنات؟
In all the societies of the bottom billion,
في كل مجتمعات المليار السفلى،
there are intense struggles to do just that.
هناك صراعات حادة لمجرد فعل ذلك.
The simple proposal is that we should have some international standards,
الإقتراح البسيط هو انه ينبغي أن نحصل على بعض المعايير الدولية،
which will be voluntary, but which would spell out the key decision points
التي ستكون طوعية، لكن من شأنها أن توضح القرارات الرئيسية
that need to be taken in order
التي ينبغي إتخاذها من أجل
to harness these resource revenues.
تسخير هذه الإيرادات من الموارد.
We know these international standards work
نحن نعلم أن هذه المعايير الدولية تنجح
because we've already got one.
لأننا بالفعل لدينا واحدة.
It's called the Extractive Industries Transparency Initiative.
إنها تسمى مبادرة شفافية الصناعات الإستخراجية.
That is the very simple idea that governments should report
إنها فكرة بسيطة للغاية حيث ينبغي على الحكومات إبلاغ
to their citizens what revenues they have.
مواطنيها بالإيرادات التي لديها.
No sooner was it proposed
ما لبثت أن أقترحت
than reformers in Nigeria adopted it, pushed it and published the revenues in the paper.
حتى تبناها الإصلاحيون في نيجيريا، دفعوها وقاموا بنشر الإيرادات في الصحف.
Nigerian newspapers circulations spiked.
إرتفع تداول الصحف النيجيرية.
People wanted to know what their government was getting
أراد الناس معرفة ما كانت الحكومة تحصل عليه
in terms of revenue.
بالنسبة للإيرادات.
So, we know it works. What would the content be of these international standards?
إذاً فنحن نعلم أنها تنجح. ماذا ستكون محتويات هذه المعايير الدولية؟
I can't go through all of them, but I'll give you an example.
لا يمكن أن تمر عبرهم جميعاً، لكني سأقدم لكم مثالاً.
The first is how to take the resources out of the ground --
الأول هو كيفية أخذ الموارد من الأرض--
the economic processes, taking the resources out of the ground
العمليات الإقتصادية، أخذ الموارد من الأرض
and putting assets on top of the ground.
ووضع الأصول على قمة الأرض.
And the first step in that is selling the rights to resource extraction.
وأول خطوة في ذلك هي بيع الحقوق لإستخراج الموارد.
You know how rights to resource extraction are being sold at the moment,
تعرفون الكيفية التي تباع بها حقوق إستخراج الموارد في هذه اللحظة،
how they've been sold over the last 40 years?
وكيف تم بيعها خلال الأربعين سنة الماضية؟
A company flies in, does a deal with a minister.
تطير الشركة إلى البلد، تعقد صفقة مع الوزير،
And that's great for the company,
وذلك عظيم بالنسبة للشركة،
and it's quite often great for the minister --
وهو بالطبع عظيم بالنسبة للوزير--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- and it's not great for their country.
-- إنه ليس عظيماً بالنسبة لبلدهم.
There's a very simple institutional technology
هناك آلية مؤسسية في غاية البساطة
which can transform that,
التي يمكن أن تغيّر ذلك،
and it's called verified auctions.
إنه تسمى التحقق من المزادات.
The public agency with the greatest expertise on Earth
الوكالة الحكومية ذات الخبرة الأعظم على الأرض
is of course the treasury -- that is, the British Treasury.
هي بالطبع الخزانة "المالية" -- التي هي، الخزانة البريطانية.
And the British Treasury decided that it would sell the rights
وقد قررت الخزانة البريطانية أنها ستبيع حقوق
to third-generation mobile phones
الجيل الثالث للهواتف النقالة
by working out what those rights were worth.
بتقييم ما كانت تساويه تلك الحقوق.
They worked out they were worth two billion pounds.
وقد قاموا بتقييمها وكانت تساوي ملياري جنيه استرليني.
Just in time, a set of economists got there and said,
تماماً في الوقت، مجموعة من الإقتصاديين وصلوا إلى هناك وقالوا،
"Why not try an auction? It'll reveal the value."
" لم لا نحاول مزاد؟ إنه سيكشف عن القيمة."
It went for 20 billion pounds through auction.
وقد وصلت إلى 20 مليار جنيه استرليني عبر المزاد.
If the British Treasury can be out by a factor of 10,
إذا كانت الخزانة البريطانية يمكن أن تخطئ بمقدار العُشر،
think what the ministry of finance in Sierra Leone is going to be like.
فكروا بماذا سيبدو عليه حال وزارة المالية في سيراليون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When I put that to the President of Sierra Leone,
عندما وضعت ذلك إلى رئيس سيراليون،
the next day he asked the World Bank to send him a team
في اليوم التالي طلب من البنك الدولي أن يرسل إليه فريق
to give expertise on how to conduct auctions.
لتقديم الخبرات حول كيفية إقامة المزادات.
There are five such decision points;
هناك خمس نقاط من مثل هذه القرارات.
each one needs an international standard.
كلٌ منها يحتاج لمعيار عالمي.
If we could do it, we would change the world.
إذا أمكننا فعلها، سنقوم بتغيير العالم.
We would be helping the reformers in these societies,
سنساعد الإصلاحيين في هذه المجتمعات
who are struggling for change.
الذين يناضلون من أجل التغيير.
That's our modest role. We cannot change these societies,
هذا هو هدفنا المتواضع. لا يمكننا تغيير هذه المجتمعات،
but we can help the people in these societies
لكننا يمكن أن نساعد الناس في تلك المجتمعات
who are struggling and usually failing,
الذين يكافحون وعادةً ما يفشلون،
because the odds are so stacked against them.
لأن التحيزات مكدسة ضدهم.
And yet, we've not got these rules.
وحتى الآن، لم نحصل على هذه القواعد.
If you think about it, the cost of promulgating international rules
إذا فكرتم بها، فان تكلفة إصدار القوانين العالمية
is zilch -- nothing.
هي لا شئ.
Why on Earth are they not there?
لماذا بحق الأرض هي غير موجودة؟
I realized that the reason they're not there
لقد أدركت أن سبب عدم وجودها
is that until we have a critical mass of informed citizens in our own societies,
هي أنه حتى يتوافر أعداد معينة من المواطنين المستنيرين في مجتمعاتنا ،
politicians will get away with gestures.
سيفلت السياسيون من التلويح.
That unless we have an informed society,
ذلك إلا إذا حصلنا على مجتمع مستنير،
what politicians do, especially in relation to Africa, is gestures:
ماذا يستطيع الساسة أن يفعلوا، خصوصاً في العلاقة مع أفريقيا، هو التلويح:
things that look good, but don't work.
أشياء تبدو جيدة، لكنها لا تنجح.
And so I realized we had to go through the business
لذا فقد أدركت أن علينا المرور عبر أعمال
of building an informed citizenry.
بناء مواطنة مستنيرة.
That's why I broke all the professional rules of conduct for an economist,
لهذا قمت بتحطيم كل قواعد سلوك الإقتصادي المهني المحترف
and I wrote an economics book that you could read on a beach.
وكتبت كتاباً إقتصادياً يمكنك قراءته على الشاطئ.
(Laughter).
(ضحك)
However, I have to say, the process of communication
لكن، ينبغي عليّ القول، أن عملية الإتصالات
does not come naturally to me.
لا تأتيني بصورة طبيعية.
This is why I'm on this stage, but it's alarming.
لهذا السبب، أنا على هذا المسرح، لكنه ينذر بالخطر.
I grew up in a culture of self-effacement.
لقد نشأت في ثقافة محو الذات.
My wife showed me a blog comment on one of my last talks,
لقد عرضت عليّ زوجتي تعليقات مدونة على أحد محادثاتي الأخيرة،
and the blog comment said, "Collier is not charismatic --
وقد قال تعليق المدونة ، " كوللر ليس كاريزمي --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- but his arguments are compelling."
-- لكن حججه مقنعة للغاية."
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If you agree with that sentiment,
إذا كنت تتفق مع ذلك الشعور،
and if you agree that we need a critical mass of informed citizenry,
وإذا كنت تتفق بأننا نحتاج لمجموعة حرجة من المواطنين المستنيرين،
you will realize that I need you.
ستدرك انني بحاجة إليك.
Please, become ambassadors.
أرجوكم أن تصبحوا سفراء.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)